Benjamin M. Tofflemire 51 Pegasi b Postdoctoral Fellow

Contact Department of Astronomy

University of Texas at Austin 2515 Speedway, Stop C1400

tofflemire@utexas.edu(503) 805-0214 tofflemire.github.io

Austin, TX 78712

Research Interests

Information

Formation and evolution of stars and planets, structure and evolution of protoplanetary disks, precise measurements of fundamental stellar parameters, signatures of stellar magnetism

Summary

Funding: \$653,200 in awards

Publications:

- First Author Publications: 9 | 210+ citations o Total Refereed Publications: 43 | 3500+ citations
- H-Index: 19
- Student Publications: 4
- Consistent growth in publications and citations over the past 5 years

Students: 8 undergrads, 6 from underrepresented groups

Mentoring: Lead UT's TAURUS mentor training, invited to lead workshop for NSF fellows Teaching: 1 new undergrad-level course co-prep, 2 semesters leading 100-level mandatory TA sections, 10+ guest lectures

Observing Experience:

- Space-based: IR, X-ray: Spitzer, XMM-Newton, Chandra
- o Ground-based: Sub-mm, IR, Optical: ALMA, Gemini South, SALT, including 800+ hours of on-site photometry and spectroscopy

Appointments

51 Pegasi b Postdoctoral Fellow, UT-Austin – Faculty Host: Prof. Adam Kraus 2020-present Postdoctoral Fellow, UT-Austin – Advisor: Prof. Adam Kraus 2018-2020 Research Assistant, UW-Madison - Advisor: Prof. Robert Mathieu 2013-2018 Research Assistant, UW-Madison – Advisor: Dr. Marina Orio 2011-2013 Research Assistant, U. of Washington – Advisor: Dr. J. Wisniewski & Prof. S. Hawley 2010-2011

EDUCATION

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Madison, WI Ph.D. Astronomy, Accretion Dynamics in Pre-Main Sequence Binary Stars July 2018 June 2013 M.S. Astronomy, Physics Minor

University of Washington B.S. Astronomy & Physics

Seattle, WA

June 2011

SELECT PEER-REVIEWED **Publications**

First Author Publications

▶ Tofflemire, B. M., Kraus, A. L., Mann, A.W., et al. (12 co-authors) 2022, AJ, submitted | ADS

A Low-Mass, Pre-Main Sequence Eclipsing Binary in the 40 Myr Columba Association - Fundamental Stellar Parameters and Modeling the Effect of Star Spots

▶ Tofflemire, B., Rizzuto, A., Newton, E., et al. (24 co-authors) 2021, AJ, 161, 171 | ADS | 20 cit.

TESS Hunt for Young and Maturing Exoplanets (THYME). V. A Sub-Neptune Transiting a Young Star in a Newly Discovered 250 Myr Association

▶ **Tofflemire**, B., Mathieu, R., Johns-Krull, C. 2019, AJ, 158, 245 | ADS | 19 cit.

Accretion Kinematics in the T Tauri Binary TWA 3A: Evidence for Preferential Accretion onto the TWA 3A Primary

▷ Tofflemire, B., Mathieu, R., Herczeg, G., Akeson, R., & Ciardi, D. 2017b, ApJL, 842, L12 | ADS | 30 cit.

Pulsed Accretion in the T Tauri Binary TWA 3A

PI-Grants & Heising-Simons Foundation Early-Faculty Development Award (\$125,000) 2022 AWARDS TESS Cycle 4 Guest Investigator Program (\$70,000) 2021 51 Pegasi b Postdoctoral Fellowship in Planetary Astronomy (\$375,000) 2020 TESS Cycle 3 Guest Investigator Program (\$75,000) 2020 University of Wisconsin Jansky Award for Outstanding Research 2017 UW-Madison Graduate School Conference Presentation Award (\$2,400) 2015, 2016, 2017 Sigma Xi Grants in Aid of Research (\$2,500) 2015 University of Wisconsin Bautz Travel Fellowship (\$1,200) 2015 University of Wisconsin Vilas Research Travel Grant (\$600) 2015 University of Washington's Astronomy Bear Prize Recipient 2011 University of Washington Mary Gates Research Scholarship (\$4,000) 2010, 2011 SELECT ALMA Cycle 7 Observing • PI: Planet Formation and Survival in Newly-Forming Binary Systems (16 hr) Programs Spitzer DDT o PI: Precision Measurements of Stellar Radii in Young Eclipsing Binaries (94 hr: Priority 1) Gemini-South • PI: The Empirical Mass-Radius Relation from 10 to 600 Myr (24 hr: Band 1) • PI: Determining Orbital Solutions for Young Eclipsing Binaries (30 hr: Band 1) Southern African Large Telescope o PI: Time-Series Spectroscopy of Pre-Main Sequence Binaries (42.5 hr: P0/P1) WIYN 3.5-m Telescope • PI: Time-series spectroscopy of flare stars in Pleiades star cluster (3 nights) SELECT STUDENT Mikayla Wilson (TCU): TAURUS Scholar 2021 RESEARCH • Characterization of a Solar Mass Eclipsing Binary • Led Research Note to the AAS o Poster to be presented at the 2023 Winter AAS • Currently: Astronomy graduate student at UC Santa Cruz Shannon Fitton (UT) 2020-2022 o Determining the Orbital Parameters of Disk-Bearing Binary Systems • Led Research Note to the AAS • Co-author on a publication in prep • Currently: Astronomy graduate student at UNC Chapel Hill Miguel Gutierrez (Florida Inst. Tech.): TAURUS Scholar 2019 o Constraining Temperature and Density of Accretion Flows in T Tauri Stars from Brackett Line Ratios o Co-Author on ApJ Publication (Kidder et al. 2021) • Led Research Note to the AAS o 2020 Winter AAS Poster o Currently: Data Scientist for Dell Technologies Victoria Catlett (UT-Dallas): UT REU 2019 Near-infrared Accretion Diagnostics of Young Stellar Objects o Co-Author on ApJ Publication (Kidder et al. 2021) • Led Research Note to the AAS 2020 Winter AAS Poster • Currently: Greenbank Telescope Software Engineer

Mentoring Training

Workshops Led

Lead Mentor Training Workshop for UT's TAURUS and REU research programs 2021,2022

Workshops Attended

o DELTA (CIRTL) Mentor Training Program

2014

• Invited to lead Mentor Training Workshop for NSF AAPF Fellow Symposium